<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors | Blas Benito</title>
    <link>/authors/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Authors</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Authors</title>
      <link>/authors/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I believe there are three significant moments in the past that led me to become the scientist I am today: learning to write simple BASIC programs with my cousin’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ZX_Spectrum&#34;&gt;ZX Spectrum&lt;/a&gt; when I was five; observing the link between topography and vegetation in the karstic mountains of Andalusia when I was a Boy-Scout; and learning how ecological modeling improves our understanding on complex biological systems while attending a theoretical ecology course taught by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.modelingnature.org/jose-maria-gomez-1&#34;&gt;Prof. José María Gómez&lt;/a&gt;. These enriching experiences motivated me to pursue a Master in Geographical Information Systems and a PhD in Global Change Ecology, and to develop an international research career working at world-class research groups, such as Ecoinfo, lead by &lt;a href=&#34;https://pure.au.dk/portal/en/svenning@biology.au.dk&#34;&gt;Jens-Christian Svenning&lt;/a&gt; (Aarhus University, Denmark), and the Ecological and Environmental Change Research Group (University of Bergen, Norway).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reaching a deeper understanding on the role of environmental drivers in shaping patterns and processes of species ecology and distributions over time and space is a pivotal topic in my research. I have focused particularly on the application of state-of-the-art quantitative methods, large-data approaches, and mechanistic modeling to answer ecological questions in a wide range of ecological systems and spatio-temporal scales.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robert Ford</title>
      <link>/authors/robert-ford/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/authors/robert-ford/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
